opera.com 2015-12-24

# Privacy Statement - Opera

The Opera browser offers excellent features for the protection of privacy and security when using Opera in the internet environment. It is Opera's policy to process personal data for purposes that are objectively justified by Opera’s service and to perform the processing in accordance with fundamental respect for the right to privacy, including the need to protect personal integrity and private life and to ensure that personal data are of adequate quality.

 _Updated December 1, 2015 - Changes to the website privacy policy_

### Privacy policies

This general part of Opera’s privacy policy contains information regarding privacy in Opera.

For privacy policies and questions specifically related to the Opera Web browser and Opera Mini, please see the appropriate section below:

  * Privacy on Opera’s web services
  * Privacy in the Opera web browser
  * Login using social services
  * Privacy in Opera Link/synchronization
  * Privacy in Opera Turbo
  * Opera’s geolocation support
  * Privacy in the Opera Mini browser
  * Privacy on our websites

#### Changes to this Privacy Statement

We will occasionally update this Privacy Statement. When we post changes to this Privacy Statement, we will include the date when the Privacy Statement was last updated. If there are material changes to this statement or in how we will use your personal information, we will notify you either by prominently posting a notice of such changes prior to implementing the change or by directly sending you a notification. We encourage you to review this Privacy Statement periodically.

###  Privacy on Opera’s web services

Opera offers web-based services. We reserve the right to add, remove, or edit any of these services. Opera  strictly protects the security of your personal information within the confines of these domains and honors your choices for their intended use. We have safeguards in place to protect your data from loss, misuse, unauthorized access, alteration, or destruction. All users should handle their and others' personal information with care. We protect your data from disclosure, with the exception of matters where designated by law or court order.

#### Processing

Personal data is collected, stored, used, and transferred only for the specific purposes mentioned in the privacy policies. Opera collects user-submitted information, IP addresses, usage patterns, and the point in time when the user visits Opera’s websites or uses Opera’s services.

#### Purposes

Processing of personal data shall be done for purposes of running, debugging, maintenance, and/or optimization of the service and/or to maintain customer relationships. Additionally, in some instances, we may also use personal data to send users information regarding update downloading, upgrades, enhancements, surveys, or advertisements.

Analysis of web or service usage (for purposes of debugging, maintenance, and optimization of service) shall never be done on a basis that reveals usage patterns of individual users, but it shall be done by aggregating data, anonymizing individual identities. Opera will not share or disclose such details except as required by law or law enforcement.

#### Access

Opera has strict restrictions on access to user data. Only a limited number of Opera employees have access.

#### Transfer

Google Analytics:  
Opera cooperates with Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google, Inc. (“Google”). Opera is using the Remarketing and Google Display Network Impression Reporting features. Opera and third-parties, including Google, use first-party cookies and third-party cookies together to a) inform, optimize, and serve ads based on someone's past visits to our website, and to b) report how our ad impressions, other uses of ad services, and interactions with these ad impressions and ad services are related visits to our site. Opera uses Google Analytics Demographics and Interest Reporting to demographic information on visitors to our website. See Google’s privacy policy for Google Analytics.  
Google Analytics is established in the United States and has entered into the Safe Harbor agreement, which entails that they must ensure an adequate standard for privacy protection in light of applicable EU rules and regulations.

Google has developed the Google Analytics Opt-out Browser Add-on to enable website visitors opt-out from get their data from the website visit collected by Google Analytics. You can also use Google's Ads Settings.

Google has developed the [Google Analytics Opt-out Browser Add-on](https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout/) to enable website visitors opt-out from get their data from the website visit collected by Google Analytics. If you are using another browser than Opera, you can also use [Google's Ads Settings](https://www.google.com/settings/ads).

Facebook:  
Opera uses Facebook Custom Audience on Opera’s web Opera and Facebook uses cookies, web beacons or similar technologies to collect or receive information from your visit to Opera’s website with the purpose to provide measurement and target ads on Facebook.

You can opt-out of this collection at: [www.aboutads.info/choices](http://www.aboutads.info/choices).

#### Correction and rectification

Users of Opera’s products and services who have provided personal information may change and modify their information at any time.

#### Retention and deletion

Opera deletes personal information when all purposes of the personal-information processing have been fulfilled.

#### Reviews

Procedures are reviewed regularly to ensure that the policies are followed. Any nonconformance regarding the policies will be corrected without unnecessary delay.

#### Security

Opera strictly protects the security of personal information within the confines of Opera’s products and services and honors the users’ choices for its intended use. We have safeguards in place to protect users’ data from loss, misuse, unauthorized access, alteration, or destruction. We protect user data from disclosure, with exceptions only in matters where designated by law or court order.

##### Children’s guidelines

Opera provides interactive environments on the internet to enable members to express themselves and to share their ideas and interests by creating and participating in discussion-based virtual communities. Opera’s corporate and community websites make no guarantees that children cannot enter these sites and present both online and offline contact information without parental consent or notification. Further, there is no guarantee that children will not post such information in a public forum. Therefore, we encourage children to include their parents in the registration process, and we encourage parents to read this Privacy Statement before allowing their children to use Opera’s services or any other internet service.

#### Contact information

If you have any questions about this Privacy Statement, privacy issues regarding Opera and our products, or privacy on our websites, we can be reached at:

Postal address:  
Opera Software ASA  
P.O. Box 4214 Nydalen  
NO-0401 OSLO  
Norway

Top

###  Privacy in the Opera web browser

Opera has taken much care in the development process so that user privacy and security are not compromised. No personal information is collected or shared. The Opera user’s web usage is not tracked.

Opera browser for computers: Your installation of Opera browser for desktop contains a unique ID that can not be linked to you as an individual person. This unique ID is required for auto-updates of the software and any installed extensions. Data about the features (not websites) used in Opera browser is collected with the purpose to improve the software and associated services. The software also creates a unique ID that is linked to your computer. This unique ID is processed with the sole purpose to measure marketing campaigns and distribution partners. Any crash logs sent by Opera browser will include the version number of the software and information about the operating system. This information is collected with the sole purpose to improve the software. Crash logs are automatically sent by default. To disable this feature select Opera > Preferences and untick “Automatically send crash reports to Opera”.

Opera for Android uses Google Analytics on Android to track referred installations to measure effects of marketing campaigns. No personal identifiable information is collected.

#### Opera’s built-in web search

Opera has a built-in web-search feature. This gives the user the option to utilize external web search engines directly from the browser interface. Opera relies on third parties for this service. The Opera web browser sends the user’s search requests (in a specially designed URL string) directly to third-party websites that handle the actual search queries. What is sent to the third-party site is only the information needed to perform the particular search query. No personal information is sent.

Some third-party sites may monitor data traffic from copies of the Opera web browser, such as numbers of hits and the search terms used. No personally identifiable information is made available to these services by the Opera Mini browser nor by Opera.

Please note: Opera does not control the privacy and security practices and policies of these third parties and their sites. Check the particular site and/or business for more information. It is the responsibility of the browser user to use caution before sharing personal information via forms and other methods used by third parties and their websites.

Top

###  Login using social services

Opera allows you to enable synchronization of browser data such as your Speed Dial entries between Opera browsers on the devices you are using, by logging in using Facebook, Google, Twitter or by creating an Opera account. Opera collects data submitted by you, and your name, username, email address and language if provided by the social service you use to log in. The data is processed with the sole purpose to enable synchronization of browser data, including debugging, improvements and optimization. Data received for a social service may be retained for up to six months after you stopped using the synchronization feature. The data in your Opera account can be modified and deleted with the tools we provide.

Top

###  Privacy in Opera Link/synchronization

Opera Link allows registered users to synchronize some data, such as bookmarks, among their Opera web browser and Opera Mini web browsers. Opera will never disclose, share, or distribute an individual’s linked data to any third party except where required by law or regulation, or in cases where you have chosen to grant access to your data to an Opera or third party application or service using Opera Link API. Opera restricts internal access to this information exclusively to those who need it for the operation of the Link service. Information user synchronizes may be stored outside of the country in which the user resides, and user hereby consents to such storage and transfer of information between jurisdictions.

Opera may retain IP addresses, user ID, and anonymous traffic data as may be useful in the debugging, optimization, and ongoing improvement of this service.

Top

###  Privacy in Opera Turbo

When Opera Turbo is enabled, the service will compress network traffic, thereby increasing download speed and reducing data volume. The service requests normal Web content through an Opera proxy server. Opera Turbo will exclude Web pages located on an intranet or by using secure connections (HTTPS). Opera collects IP addresses, usage patterns, and the point in time at which the service is used for the purpose debugging, maintenance, optimization of the service, or maintaining the customer relationship. Analysis of service usage is conducted by aggregating data, anonymizing individual identities.

Top

###  Opera’s geolocation support

Opera browsers with support for [geolocation](http://help.opera.com/Mac/12.10/en/geolocation.html) enable users to share their geographic location with websites. If the user chooses to share their location with a web service, they have to enable geolocation support. The location service is provided by Google and is governed by [Google’s privacy policy](http://m.google.com/privacy). The requesting websites’ use of your location is governed by the respective websites’ privacy policies. Opera encourages users only to share their location with websites they trust.

If you use those services, Google receives information about your actual location (such as GPS signals sent by a mobile device) or information that can be used to approximate a location (such as a cell ID). Opera does not receive or store any location information. Google returns your location (longitude, latitude and accuracy) and your location is made available to the website by the Opera browser through the W3C Geolocation API.

Top

###  Privacy in the Opera Mini browser

Opera Mini is a web browsing service relying on web pages being pre-rendered on Opera Mini servers and then sent to the Opera Mini client on your device. Opera is not able to link usage related data in Opera Mini servers to individual persons.

Opera Mini servers logs in addition to the web addresses (not content of the web pages), IP-addresses, the end-user device make and model, any campaign reference for the Opera Mini client and a randomly generated identifier for the Opera Mini client. Opera stores and processes usage related log data to provide, debug, maintain and optimize the service including populating “My sites” and “My news” in Home on supported clients. The “Home” can be disabled in Menu > Settings > Advanced > Home page On/Off. Usage related log data are also used to generate aggregated and anonymized statistics for Opera’s own use and for reporting usage to Opera’s customers such as mobile network operators.

Opera Mini collects device information on Android for the purpose of product improvements and to measure marketing campaigns. This data might be shared with Opera's marketing partners/customers. No personal identifiable information is collected.

Opera Mini on Android uses the AdMarvel SDK provided by AdMarvel, Inc for advertisement in the Opera browser and/or on websites accessed with the browser. No personal identifiable information is collected. [AdMarvel privacy policy](http://www.admarvel.com/AdMarvel_Privacy_Policy_2012.pdf). The AdMarvel SDK includes Facebook SDK for Android with the purpose to receive advertisement from Facebook. Privacy policy: <https://www.facebook.com/policy.php>

Opera Mini server logs are kept for up to six months. Usage related log data are also used to generate aggregated and anonymized statistics for Opera’s own use and for reporting usage to Opera’s customers such as mobile network operators.

Opera Mini will receive cookies from visited websites and when you are using the built-in, search-related features. These cookies can be removed in Menu > Tools > Settings > Privacy.

In the case Opera has a contractual relationship with your mobile operator, the mobile operator might send additional data such as your phone number together with the web traffic. Opera will pass on such additional data to your mobile operator's approved list of partners. Please note that Opera does not receive, log or retain such additional data in any way or manner.

Opera reserves the right to disclose any information we have as required by law and when we believe that disclosure is necessary to protect our rights and/or comply with a judicial proceeding, court order, or legal process.

#### Opera Mini’s built-in web search

Opera Mini has a built-in, web-search feature. This gives the user the option to utilize external web search engines directly from the browser interface. Opera Mini relies on third parties for this service. Opera Mini sends the user’s search requests (in a specially designed URL string) directly to third-party websites that handle the actual search queries. What is sent to the third-party site is the special Opera Mini search string along with the text terms needed to perform the particular search query. No personal information is sent.

When using the built-in, search-related features, Opera Mini will receive cookies, including third-party cookies, from third-party sites. These can be removed using  _Tools > Settings > Privacy_ from the menu in Opera Mini.

Some third-party sites may monitor data traffic from copies of the Opera Mini browser, such as numbers of hits and the search terms used. No personally identifiable information is made available to these services by the Opera Mini browser nor by Opera.

Please note: Opera does not control the privacy and security practices and policies of these third parties and their sites. Check the particular site and/or business for more information. It is the responsibility of the browser user to use caution before sharing personal information via forms and other methods used by third parties and their websites.

Top

###  Privacy on our websites

The following statement discloses the information gathering and dissemination practices for Opera.com and other Opera domains.

#### Collection of data

##### IP Addresses

Opera will occasionally collect visitors’ IP addresses to help diagnose problems with servers and to administer websites. IP addresses will not be used for any other purpose.

##### Information collected from forms

Opera.com and other Opera domains use forms for visitors to request information, products, and services. Depending on the service, product, or information that visitors request, visitors’ contact information (e.g., email addresses or telephone numbers) or financial information (e.g., credit-card numbers) may be collected. Contact information from these forms is used to send orders and information about Opera to customers. Visitors’ contact information is also used to contact them when necessary. Visitors may opt out of receiving future mailings; see the Choice/opting out section. Financial information that is collected is used to bill the user for products and services.

##### Cookies

Opera does not have access to any information about visitors from cookies received while visiting Opera’s sites. While Opera websites generally do use cookies, they are used primarily for such purposes as session management and retaining the user’s custom settings or preferences.

##### Survey

Opera’s online surveys ask visitors for demographic information (e.g., age, internet usage, or income level). This is not personally identifying information and is used to tailor the visitors’ experience at Opera’s websites.

##### Contests

Opera runs contests in which visitors are requested to provide contact information (e.g., email addresses). Visitors’ contact information is used to contact the visitor when necessary and is deleted after its purpose is fulfilled. This information will not be shared with nor sold to other parties. Users may opt out of receiving future mailings.

#### Public forums

Various Opera websites make web forums, mailing lists, and news groups available to visitors. Please remember that any information that is disclosed in these areas becomes public information, and visitors should exercise caution when deciding to disclose personal information.

#### Transfer

Opera Software uses Cxense on Opera's website to collect or receive information from your visit to Opera's website with the purpose to create a better user experience and if relevant to create better advertising when promoting Opera consumer products. The Cxense's privacy policy is located: <https://www.cxense.com/about/privacy-policy/>

We use Universal Event Tracking (UET) from Microsoft Bing Ads (<http://advertise.bingads.microsoft.com/en-us/privacy-policy>) for advertising and marketing purposes. Page URL, page title, and some non-personally identifiable information (session ID, screen height, width, color depth, language) is send to Bing Ads.

#### Links to other sites

Opera websites contain links to other sites. Opera is not responsible for the privacy practices or the content of such websites.

#### Choice/opting out

Opera.com provides users the opportunity to op out of receiving communications from Opera and its partners at the point where information is requested about the visitor.

Top
